As I said welcome back to the channel
and today we will see that how
configuration property is useful for us.
So but let's first see the problem then
we will come back to this uh topic. So
let's first see what the issue with the
add the rate value annotation. We have
already covered this right. So add the
rate value is good for injecting a
single property but it become pro
problematic as configuration grows. So
we know that we have certain properties
in application
dotproperty
file. Okay. And with add the rate value
we can inject that property into our
Java code. Okay. How like this? Let's
say I have a class DB connection. Okay.
And I have this field string username.
So there in application.properties
there would be one config like app dot
username.
Okay. And whatever the value would be.
So that I am injecting from my property
file to this field like this. Okay. So
we have already covered this. So we have
to use this annotation add the rate
value and then we have to use this
placeholder and the
property name what we have to inject.
Okay. Now the problem is that if there
are let's say a group of configuration
which you have to use then it's always
one to one mapping. So if you have to
inject 10 values you have to do 10 times
add the rate value add the rate value
add the rate value likewise okay so one
thing is it's too much duplication of
add the rate value annotation or
duplication in the sense is not like uh
same configuration I mean you have to
use a lot of this annotation let's say
if you know you are working in a big
tech organization definitely you know
that 100,000
like these These are very very commonly
faced challenge in uh these tech
companies like configuration
continuously grows and lot of things are
configurationdriven itself. Okay. So we
have a huge number of configuration.
Now if you have to do one to one mapping
just see how many times or how many
places we have to use this annotation.
Okay. So that is the first problem. The
second problem is there is no way to
validate. Validate in the sense like I
want to say that hey okay this password
which is coming from the
application.property it should be
present. It should be greater than 10
and less than 25 in size. There is no
way to validate or put restriction
and top of it. Okay. So once you have
got the value from the
application.properties properties after
that you have to manually do the
validation that whatever the value I
receive it's valid or not okay so
consider this two major problem which
add the rate value has and now
add the rate configuration properties
comes into the picture. Okay. So now it
would be easy to understand why at the
rate configuration properties is very
popular among industry. Okay.
So it maps configuration
from application.properties into Java
object. This is important not to a one
field to a Java object. Okay. So it
makes our configuration structured,
reusable and validated. How? Once you
have the Java object, you can reuse it.
You can pass it to different classes.
Correct? You can have validation on top
of it. How? I will also tell you. Okay?
So, validation is very easy through
annotations.
Okay? And it's now structured. We have a
proper Java like you you can group
together particular. Let's say these are
my uh invoice
configuration. These are my sales
configuration. So you can group in a
Java object like configuration depend
upon certain logical grouping you can
do. Okay. So we can create some
structured
configuration
uh which can be validated which can be
reused.
So now see this example
application.properties.
So here I have certain configuration
like user.name name certain name user
dot age user doactive so now how can I
use it so now see this
we have to create one Java class okay so
let's say I created one user
configuration because I want to group
all the configuration related to user
into one class okay into one object so I
created a class user configuration
I annotated with at the rate component.
So I am telling that hey spring you
create an object for this. Okay. Now I
am also adding the annotation at the
rate configuration properties.
Okay. So whenever you add this
annotation
there is something called
configuration
binding.
So its task is to bind between
application
do.properties
and your Java object. Okay. So it helps
in binding. Okay. So now I am adding
this annotation at the rate
configuration properties and I give the
prefix any property start with user. So
any property start with user is fall
under this. So it's like user dotster.
So it will catch all and it will try to
map
each
application.property into this field
now.
Okay. So now this is clear. Now I have
to create a field. So one is like name.
So I created the exact same name. Okay.
So generally okay there is certain
relaxation. Let's say here you have is
hyphen enabled something like this. So
you can hear create is enabled camel
case. Okay. So these are allowed. Okay.
You won't face any problem that if you
have used underscore here or hyphen here
you you can't use like how you will use
here. You also have to use underscore
here. No. Okay. So if you use a camel
case properly it would be able to do
proper mapping.
But I would always recommend that try to
make a same name. the same name so that
the mapping would be like we are 100%
sure okay because see this mapping is
not controlled by us it is done by
configuration binding so it might be
possible that uh it not able to bind
certain property
okay so now here if you see that I keep
the same name so this name would get
bind to this one this age will get bind
to this field and this active get bind
to this boolean
okay so Now what will happen when you
start an application? When you start an
application,
let's say we have annotated with at the
rate component. So means a spring will
create an empty bean first. It will
create an empty bean. We have already
discussed the life cycle of a bean in
the starting of the series if you recall
it. Okay. So first spring create an
empty bean because using
default
constructor.
Now once empty bean is created. Now okay
and uh now the configuration binding
during application startup only I'm
saying configuration binding what it
will do is it will try to fill up these
values. So during empty bean these all
have default values name would be let's
say null age would be zero active would
be false these are all default values
say okay now configuration binding would
bind would read the application.property
property. Okay. And try to do the
binding. Okay. Try to fill up this value
using what? Using setter
method. Okay. So, we need to have a
getter and setters. Okay. Configuration
binding is you going to use setter
method to fill up these values using
application.properties.
Okay. Since we have already uh done add
the rate component bean was already
present but it's an empty bean means all
it has default values and configuration
binding now calling setter method to
update these values through
application.properties.
Okay.
Now whatever the user configuration
class you have created or bean you have
created you can simply inject it into
whichever class you want. Okay. And use
like a normal Java object like I am
using user configuration dot get age get
name is active. And here you can see
that I am able to print it.
Okay. So this is how simple it is. Now
also you can see that you can properly
like group the configurations logical
grouping you can do you can reuse it
okay you don't have to create another
class for you reusing it again and again
once you have created it now you can
autowire it anywhere in the code base
you want.
Okay,
one more advantage of this is like you
can handle nested complex configuration
nested complex. Now here if you see the
first thing this is simple we have
already seen that now see this two what
I'm doing here is user dot so this would
be handled by my this configuration
okay here I have put at the rate
configuration properties prefix equals
to user so this configuration or this
class configuration binding would be
used to handle all user dotest because
this is the prefix user. Okay. So for
now any configuration starting with user
dot configuration binding going to use
this class.
Now here if you see I have address dot
city address dot country. So means we
can create address as an object and
these two can be field inside it. So
that's where I have done. Okay. So here
what I have done is I have created
address config one nested class. Okay,
within this
user configuration, within this class,
there is a nested
class we are creating and okay, I gave a
name address config and it has two field
city and country. So, I have the same
naming I have used. So, okay, it's
getter and setter and getter and setter
of all this one.
Okay. And one thing is that I have
specifically made it a static a static
nested class. You can think of like why
static why not non-static. If you
remember in the Java series we have
already covered this nested class. Okay.
So nested class can be of static
non-static. Okay. So why specifically
here we have to use static. So the thing
is how spring manage the bean. So see
this flow with that you will get an
answer generally like why static we have
to create okay in this case whenever we
are trying to do configuration binding
only in case I'm telling you whenever we
are trying to do configuration binding.
Okay um in this case we always create an
static nested class. Reason is first a
spring creates user configuration bean
because it add the red component. So
user will creates its empty bean. Okay.
Now it will see a field address
configuration. Okay. So it now this
it see this okay now what it will do
once it's create an empty bean after
that I'm saying empty bean is created.
Now configuration
binder
got invoked. Now it is using the setter
methods to uh set name age active from
the application.properties.
Okay. Now binder sees that uh address
doconfig. Now it has to
update the field of this. Okay. Now what
it will do is it uses internally
reflection and try to initiate the type
address config using the default no r
constructor.
So internally binding calls the so it
has to create an object
of first address config.
It has to create an object of this and
after that it use it calls it setter
method. Okay. And to create an object of
it, it call the default constructor.
Default
constructor.
Okay. Now understand that when you are
not defining it static, let's say it is
non-static.
What if you can recall from from our
Java series if you are following that
whenever we create a nest uh nested
class and it's a non-static what is the
default constructor? Default constructor
generally is your address config and it
takes a parameter of your
parent
class user configuration let's say UC.
So this is the default constructor which
generally added even though I haven't
written this constructor internally the
default constructor it add is this not
the default constructor with no argument
this don't get added for the nested
class for non-static this is the default
constructor added and if you can recall
we used to call it that hey user
configuration object dot new and then
your address config like this. Okay. So
internally it always pass the reference
of your parent object to here.
Okay. So one thing we are clear that
when we are using non-static then
default constructor which get added is
which take a reference of the parent
object. Okay. But the binder reflection
try to invoke the no arg constructor.
Now if there is if this is non-static no
arg means constructor which do not take
any argument that doesn't even exist. So
it will not work. Your binding will
fail. Your binding will fail. Your
binder will fail. So that's why we have
make it static. So when you make it
static means it is not associated with
your parent class. Okay. And then the
default constructor which got added is
the no arg constructor. Okay. So your
address config and the constructor which
don't take any argument that will get
added. Okay. And that's why here binder
able to work. So that's why it is always
created a static nested object.
Okay.
So yeah now come back to this one. Let's
say I have a user inside this address
dot city user dot address dot country.
So what I did is I created address as an
object and all later one it's a field
inside a address. Okay. And since this
is inside the user I created a nested a
static nested class.
Okay.
And you can easily use it like uh there
is like no problem at all like how we
are going to create an uh object simple
in that way you can use it.
So this is one way of handling the
nested complex configuration.
Now we can also handle the configuration
as list.
Okay. See this one. Now we have already
seen this one the simple one object one.
So this is object this is simple direct
mapping. Now this is we are telling you
the list. Okay. So list I'm telling you
the two flavor list of string list of
object. So let's see first the list of a
string. So let's say your configuration
looks like this. User.0
admin user. One editor. Likewise you
have this. So the same at the rate
component I want a spring to create an
object. Add the red configuration
properties and prefix user. So all the
anything starting with user dot
ultimately comes to this class. Okay. So
name age active and this one we have
already seen. Okay. So this is its
static nested class we have already
seen. Now this is the list one. So
what's the field name? Roles. Okay. And
what values generally putting a string.
Okay. So simply I put list of string
and I put it getter and setter method.
Okay. It will automatically bind 01 in
the same order to this one.
Similarly here if you see user now here
I have course zero dot name course 0
enroll true similarly I have course one
dot name course one dot enroll okay so
now here if you see course you can
visualize like course is an object which
has name and enroll fields and we have
zero one. So two objects of it. Okay. So
it's an array of course. So it's an
array of object. Okay. So this is the
example. So now here if you see the list
of course. Now again the course would be
static nested class. So static nested
class here in this one. Okay. So it is
inside a user and I already told you why
it need to be static. Okay. So now what
two fields it has name and enrolled. So
I have the same field name and enrolled.
It's getter and setter and ultimately
the getter and setter for this one. So
it will be able to do proper mapping. So
here here I am using it user
configuration.get
roles get zero get one. It would be the
same order you will get admin editor.
Similarly courses I am printing get
quotes get zero its name and the get one
get name. So Java springboard
the same order.
Okay. So we can also
bind the list in application.properties
to a list in Java object. Similarly
configuration as map. Now here if you
see
see this one. So we have already seen
different uh here again this is just to
remind this is simple direct mapping
this is object
this is your
list
and now we are seeing the map. So now
see this one user dot preference dot
theme user.preference dot language
user.preference preference time zone.
Let's say your requirement is you want
to store in a map is like theme
dark
language en so it's a string
comma string let's say you want to store
like this
then
even this this now you can say that here
can you see that can with any other way
can you handle it without even map so
here if you see user dot So this class
going to this prefix class going to
handle it. Okay. Now you say that
preference dot theme preference dot
language preference dot time zone. You
can say that hey I can create an object
of preferences
and these are all
fields within a preference. That's what
we did for the object.
Yes, you can do that also. Okay. And if
you want you can also handle through a
map. So this preference become your map
name. So here I created a map string
comma string and preferences this become
my map field name and this is key. This
is value key value. Key value. Okay. So
now here if you see just getter and
setter now it will bind like this become
your key. This is value. This is key.
This is value. This is key. This is
value. That is also possible. But if you
want to use as an object, create a
nested class and uh a static nested
class and create a preference as an
object that is also possible like what
we did for the address.
Okay. But alternatively, you can also
create a key like this. So this is your
map field name and this is your becomes
your key value. And this is how I'm able
to use it. So this is my map, right? Get
preference, get key name, theme. Okay,
so it works.
Similarly, map of an object. So this is
here if you see it's a map string, a
string. So we can also extend it to the
map of an object. So see this is an
example
user dot. Okay. So anything is starting
with user going to ultimately to the
user configuration because that's the
prefix. So that's till now we are clear.
Now here if you see what the
configuration look like locations dot
home dot city
locations dot dot country location dot
office dot city location dot office dot
country okay. So what do you see here?
So here if you see
this location
can be our map field name.
Okay. So I created first thing is map
field name. Okay. Now here if you see
this becomes my like a string home
office. So my map is like
home and now I'm creating an object
which has city country city country okay
then I have a key office
then I have let's say this is an object
office city office dot country so I have
an object which has the city country
okay so this is just like you can also
handle through an object object but I
want to handle through a map. So like
this we can do that. So this become my
map whatever the map I'm going to create
it's field name then these become my key
and internally this become like an
object which has this values.
So this is how I did it like map string
address config. So here I already have
an address config right from previous
one. Okay, I already have a static
nested class. So, address config has the
city and country. That's why I use the
same field city and country. Okay, so
I am creating a map of a string, address
config. So, a string going to be this
one either home or either office. Okay.
And address config has this city
country. Okay. And this location is the
my field name.
That's all the getter and setter.
Now it will properly bind it. So it will
look for the map which has this name. So
it found this. Okay. Then it will store
the key. This become your key home. So
it will create one home. And then this
city home dot city home dot country. So
this city and country it will see that
okay address config is the object. So it
will get this object bind this city and
country and store it here.
So we can even create complex map
objects also and you can simply use it
like this normal how Java object is used
to access the values.
Okay, you are able to get the location.
Okay. So till now it's clear that we can
map even the complex configurations
in our Java objects either it's a list
list of object map of object normal
object direct values everything we can
do that
now another advantage is the validations
spring boot automatically validate
fields after binding
before the app fully starts. So one
thing is you have to add this dependency
spring boot starter validation because
this will add enable certain annotations
which we are going to use.
So first thing is we need to add add the
rate validated annotation on top of our
add the configuration property class.
Okay. And also remember that whenever
any validation fail application will not
even start itself. So see this example
now this is very simple one. I created
at the rate component I want a spring to
create a bean. Add the red configuration
property means after the MTB is created
by spring configuration binding
will start its work and it will bind all
the configuration starting with user to
its fields. Now I also put validated
means all the annotations which I am
going to add now that need to be
validated. Okay. So now here if you see
I have put add the rate not blank
message and I give the messages name
must not be empty on the top of this
name. So now here if you see what I'm
trying to do is adding a validation.
Okay, whatever the value. So first
sequence is
empty bean.
Second is binding
like binding is your property
to object and the third is validation.
Okay. So validate what it will validate?
it will validate the value of these
fields whatever the annotation we have
to use okay let's say that for the age I
have used the annotation add the rate
min value equals to one so means the
minimum value of the age should be one
okay and for the testing purpose in
application.properties I have put zero
okay so when you start an application
itself it says that failed
H cannot be zero whatever the message
you have given.
Okay, your validation fails. So see how
easy it is to validate the values which
are coming from application.properties.
Okay. And there are so many validations
which we can use like at the rate not
null you can use like this value cannot
be null. Not blank means not null, not
empty. Okay. So here like uh not empty
you can use it on top of list and map
that it should have certain values. Add
the red min, minimum value, add the red
max. If you want to define what is the
maximum value, positive or you can use
positive or zero. It's like greater than
0, greater than equals to 0. Similarly
at the rate negative, at the rate
negative or 0, less than 0 or less than
equals to 0. Okay. So there are
different reaxes. If you see that these
are nothing but like hibernate if you
have seen the hibernate validations
right it is very similar to that one
internally actually it use that only
okay so if you are familiar with
hibernate we have seen the hibernate
validations also previously okay so it's
very similar to that one only.
Now last thing would be like one
questions comes to our mind. Okay. Sh
one doubt.
What we are saying is currently till our
sequences we are creating an empty bean.
Why? Because we have used at the rate
component.
This is very important. So see the
sequence and then see the answer also.
The second thing is we are saying
configuration binding
configuration binding.
What it will do is it will use the
setter method
and invokes the setter method to update
update the fields
using application
dotproperties.
Now what if I have to make my
configuration class immutable?
Okay, generally this is how the
interviewer asks the uh interview
question generally that how you can make
your configuration properties class
immutable.
Okay, because let's say you have given
an answer through at the rate component
one then definitely the sequence going
to be like this. First bean would be
created and after that configuration
binding has to invoke the setter method
to update the values and whenever you
have a setter method definitely it's not
an immutable class. Immutable class
means once you have defined the value it
cannot be changed. Okay. But if this is
the how we are doing this currently it
is definitely not immutable. Why? First
during empty bean let's say age is zero.
Then during configuration binding it
call the setter method. update it with
the whatever the property value it has.
Let's say I have defined 27. So you are
changing it. Definitely it's not an
immutable. So now the question of uh the
ask question intention is how you can
make this configuration class immutable
generally which is very important.
Once you read the configuration from the
properties it should not be changed by
anyone. So this is very very important
and this is how actually it's used in
the industry. It should be immutable.
So answer is constructor binding.
Okay. So see this how we can do that
very very simple. Okay. But very minor
you can say that uh observation here
what we are doing. So first I created
earlier the class name was user
configuration. I just changed the name
to immutable user configuration. Nothing
same thing. Okay. Now here I make the
all the fields final.
Now constructor binding as the name says
so we going to be using constructor
when the object is first time object is
going to get create at the time of
creation of the object itself I'm going
to initialize this so immutable user
configuration I'm creating a constructor
and all the fields
okay and that going to initialize at the
time of object creation itself okay so
it's not first like you are going to
create an empty bean or no whenever
somebody has to create an object it has
to pass this value and at the time of
object creation itself these values
would be set
okay so this is going to be the thing
and then here I have only getter methods
no setter method now see what things we
needed one thing you notice that there
is no add the rate component I removed
it why because as soon as you put at the
rate component
means you are telling a spring that hey
you manage the creation of an object
okay and when spring going to manage the
creation of an object spring doesn't
know how to or what value I need to
provide here
what value I need to provide here what
name I need to provide here what age I
need to provide here what active I need
to provide here okay so spring
Or you can say that spring IOC inversion
of control doesn't know how to invoke
this constructor what value I need to
pass. So
at the rate component that's why I
removed it. Okay. And I gave this
responsibility to configuration
binding itself. Okay. earlier
configuration binding sees that hey okay
whatever the user configuration I have
it's object is already present yes
object is already present yes then call
the setter method to update the values
now we just need to tell that hey you
also have to take the responsibility of
creation the object also okay and that's
we do by like this in our main class
application class we have to tell Add
the rate configuration properties scan.
So whenever you add this configuration
whenever you add this annotation at the
rate configuration properties scan what
we are telling to the configuration
binding that hey I am giving the
responsibility to you to create an
object for this configuration class
property class also.
Okay. So I am not relying on a spring.
I'm giving the responsibility to
configuration binding itself that you
create an object. Okay. And when
it scan for it so it knows so it first
read application.properties.
Okay. And then
when it find this object find this class
it need to invoke its constructor. It
will do the binding. Okay. What value
exact it has to pass. Now it knows
because it has read from
application.properties. properties.
Okay. So at the time of con uh creation
of a new object, this value would be
set. Okay. And there are no setters and
these are final. So now our class is
immutable.
So these
this is the only change. No add the rate
component. You only got why because
spring doesn't know what value I need to
pass. Okay. So that's why spring won't
be able to create an object of it. So
that's why we I have removed it at that
component. I don't want to give you the
responsibility
and who knows what value to pass is
configuration binding because it reads
the application.property. So this is how
we tell okay at the rate configuration
property scan on top of your main class
application class.
Okay. But you might be thinking hey
earlier why it's not an issue earlier
whatever we are doing it when it is not
immutable. See earlier it's not an issue
because even though we have used at the
rate component okay
there we have default constructor
default constructor which is no arg
constructor so our spring inversion of
control can create an empty bean create
an empty bean by calling a no arg
constructor so that's why at the rate
component was working properly it able
to create an object through calling the
default no constructor. Okay. And then
configuration binding calling setter
method to update it. But here in the
immutable since we don't have setter
method. Okay. And we don't have this
default constructor no or constructor.
Okay. So that's why add the rate
component will not work
and that's where configuration bindings
comes into the picture.
Okay. And here if you see it worked
properly. Our immutable objects work
properly. And also there is no
difference in the validation of the
field like how we used to validate the
field like add the rate minimum uh add
the rate not null like in uh nonmutable
class like similarly for the mutable
also it's the same thing you can use
above the field itself.
Okay. I hope this is clear. Add the rate
configuration properties. If there is
any doubt let me know. We can discuss
further in the comment section.